<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Libertas, or Reliefe to the English captives in Algier. Briefly discoursing hovv such as are in slavery may be soonest set at liberty, others preserved therein, and the great Turke reduc'd to renue and keepe the peace inviolate, to a greater enlargement of trade and priviledges than ever the English nation hitherto enjoy'd in Turkie. Presented to the serious consideration of the honourable Court of Parliament. / By Henry Robinson, gent.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1674</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E173_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858894</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E173[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Libertas, or Reliefe to the English captives in Algier. Briefly discoursing hovv such as are in slavery may be soonest set at liberty, others preserved therein, and the great Turke reduc'd to renue and keepe the peace inviolate, to a greater enlargement of trade and priviledges than ever the English nation hitherto enjoy'd in Turkie. Presented to the serious consideration of the honourable Court of Parliament. / By Henry Robinson, gent.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Rich. Cotes for John Sweeting, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Angel, in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Turkey --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Algeria --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110954:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIBERTAS, OR RELIEFE TO THE ENGLISH CAPTIVES IN <hi>ALGIER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly diſcourſing how ſuch as are in ſlavery may be ſooneſt ſet at Liberty, others preſerved therein, and the Great <hi>Turke</hi> reduc'd to renue and keepe the Peace inviolate, to a greater enlargement of Trade and Priviledges than ever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation hitherto enjoy'd in <hi>Turkie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preſented to the ſerious Conſideration of the Honourable Court of</hi> Parliament.</p>
            <p>BY HENRY ROBINSON, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Rich. Cotes</hi> for <hi>John Sweeting,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſigne of the Angel, in Popes-head Alley. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110954:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110954:2"/>
            <head>RELIEFE FOR THE ENGLISH <hi>CAPTI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES</hi> IN ALGIER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Undry propoſitions have beene made for redemption of our Captives in <hi>Algier;</hi> Some take it to be a worke of Charity to Ranſome them, and queſtionleſſe it were ſo, but that their ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes will ſo much more encourage and enable thoſe Pyrates to take them ſlaves againe, and twice as many more; Others conceive a Fleete of twenty Ships at Sea for about five yeares together, would be their utter ruine, by making prize of them if they ſtirr'd out, or rot and periſh if they keepe at home: but how doubtfull the ſucceſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110954:3"/>may be, will appeare by ſundry reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe our Fleet cannot alwayes ſo ride be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Algier,</hi> but their ſhips (obſerving all advantages) will paſſe both out and in, though with ſome haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard.</p>
            <p>Secondly, being once but out of reach, they doe not onely out-ſaile us, but at Sea, worſe than in a wood, are hardly to be met withall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it would be a long and chargeable peece of worke, for what if we ſhould take five or ten of them in a yeare? the reſt would likely take ſome of ours in lieu thereof; and being above a hundred ſaile at preſent, to take but ten a yeare, and more we are not likely, would prove a ten yeares taske and charge unto us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the leave we have of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> is onely to take Pyrates of <hi>Algier,</hi> but how ſhall we diſtinguiſh the Pyrates from others of <hi>Algier?</hi> For ſcarce ever a ſhip of them, but is both Merchant, and a Pyrate, many times in the ſelfe-ſame voyage: I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeve not one of them but deſires to be ſo, and wants onely opportunity: Now ſince every ſhip ſeekes for conveniency to play the Pyrate, and yet unleſſe taken in the fact, may ſtill pretend to be a Merchant-man, what good can our Fleet effect in ſo milde a way? To hinder them from comming out of Port, you may not, as contrary to our Articles of Peace with them, ſince they will all, though never ſo many, pretend a Merchants voyage, without giving you leave to ſearch their Cockets, meet with them where or when you can at Sea, they are ſtill Marchant-men, unleſſe they have taken a prize, and then too, for how can we hinder them in a Merchants voyage, to take their enemies, whether <hi>Italians, French, Spaniards, Dutch,</hi> or any Nation elſe, but <hi>Engliſh?</hi> So that the caſe ſtands thus; keepe as many Fleetes as you will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110954:3"/>abroad, you may not keepe the Pyrates from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of Port: meete with them as often as you can at Sea, unleſſe you light upon thoſe very ſhips, which have firſt prey'd upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> three fourthes whereof will likely ſcape you, our labour is all in vaine; Nor can much be replyed to this Objection, for though the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> give us leave to take the <hi>Algier</hi> Pyrates, it is not becauſe he meanes really we ſhall take them, that may ſo much ſtead him in all attempts, as hereafter appeares more plainely, but becauſe he thinkes we cannot; and if we could, and did, what ere our Capitulations be, his expoſition will be ſuch as ſhall make us pay deere for taking them: So that whilſt we have eſtate in <hi>Turkie,</hi> every Pyrate taken, will be a Merchant-man, the taking whereof, much more a number of them, would doubtleſſe prove a breach of Peace, eſpecially being his owne Interpreter, as is well knowne to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants coſt, upon all occaſions, and Ambaſſador, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whole effects, endangered no leſſe than if we had ſacked <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, grant we might and could ruine at laſt this neſt of Robbers, which in likelihood, by reaſon of their Situation, we cannot be able for one or two yeares ſpace, to damnifie ſo much, as we might the Imperiall ſeate it ſelfe, and whole Territories beſides on the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Coaſt; Yet if after many yeares charge and trouble it were effected, the rooting out this one Nation might chance bring in Dominion of ſeverall others into thoſe parts, and prove more peſtiferous to us in matter of our commerce for the future: So that unleſſe the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> will give us leave to aſſault them all, Men of Warre and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, both by Sea and Land, as they doe us at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whereby to force them to a friendſhip, it may prove neceſſary for us to make open warre againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110954:4"/>him, and how by this courſe it may not onely be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but that this courſe is the moſt probable (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my ſelfe notwithſtanding, to better judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) likelyeſt to be more beneficiall in the end, and of leſſe charge and detriment in the atchieving, may happily thus be made appeare.</p>
            <p>The moſt conſiderable benefit redounding to this Kingdome by the <hi>Turkie</hi> Trade, is the annuall expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of above twenty thouſand Broad cloath, dyed and dreſſed in their full manufacture for theſe latter yeares, what we bring home in returne thereof, is not ſo materiall, as Silke, Cotton wooll, Cotton yarne, Galls, Grograines, Grograine yarne, &amp;c. all or moſt whereof we can have elſe where, or be without in caſe of neceſſity, and for the moſt part, to further theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes, about fifty thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> uſed to be ſent from <hi>Legorne</hi> unto <hi>Aleppo,</hi> in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Reals of <hi>eight,</hi> which otherwiſe might perhaps have beene brought for <hi>England</hi> in <hi>ſpecie,</hi> and at worſt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, or in ſome commodities or other; and it is worth notice, that though the <hi>Turkie</hi> company have of late thus exported above twenty thouſand col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd clothes <hi>per annum,</hi> yet it is certaine, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, as the caſe ſtands, continue the trade to profit for above halfe that quantity in the future, unleſſe the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Cloath be yet farther beaten out, which (by the way) may very likely take effect, if abſtaining from ſending falſe-made cloath, the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and charges were taken off here in <hi>England,</hi> and we thereby enabled to under-ſell them.</p>
            <p>This I conceive, is the true ſtate of the <hi>Turkie</hi> trade; together with the utmoſt benefit, (except the venting of a little Tin) to be put into the ballance againſt the inconveniencies we ſuffer for this Trades ſake, to the diſhonour of God, and the King, and prejudice of the Common weale, which is by ſuffering ſome foure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110954:4"/>or five thouſand of his Majeſties loving Subjects to remaine in chaines, and leaving the reſt liable to be carried away Captives at theſe Pyrates pleaſure, haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding the loſſe of their very Soules as well as bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; wherewith, queſtionleſſe, God is much offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and will one day take account thereof, and the Kings Majeſty no little diſhonour'd by keeping Peace with Infidels, upon ſuch diſ-advantages, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Subjects, not onely to give Merchandize for Merchandize, and money to boote, to our Countries common prejudice, but when we ſhall have carryed them our Commodities, and monies to their owne houſes, (a great conveniency to thoſe effeminate la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy people) and laden with their Country Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities for our returnes, to ſuffer both us, our Ships, and returnes, as ſoone as we are out of Port, to be taken Captive by Subjects of the ſame Prince; which, it is true, he therefore calls Pyrates, but onely the better to delude Chriſtians, for he can command them if he pleaſe, and if he could not, might at leaſt give us leave to right our ſelves; the latter is unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, and the other is proved ſince nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, but that he may as well hereafter, in that he did command them heretofore, and they in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence kept the Peace ſome yeares together, and pretend even to this day, not to continue it, becauſe we broke it firſt; which perhaps may in part be true, but was in way of Pyracy, not countenanced by our State, and in ſuch caſes Juſtice, and equity require onely that reſtitution be made, which we may proffer now on our part, and demand the like from them, that cannot be declin'd, if they meane really: and this will yet appeare more plainely, even on the Grand <hi>Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors</hi> part too, in that he, or his Miniſters by him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very three yeares ſubſtituted, have the Hull or tenths of every Ship or <hi>Engliſh</hi> prize is taken; And how
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110954:5"/>prejudiciall it is to this Commonwealth, to loſe ſo many Ships, the ſtrength and ſafety of the Kingdome, ſo much money and Merchandize, the wealth and riches of the Kingdome, and ſo many men all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, able to winne and keepe a Kingdome, were it but lawfull for them, needes no Rhetorique to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
            <p>And ſince we ſpeake of the <hi>Turkie</hi> trade, ſo famous not onely over <hi>England,</hi> but all parts of the knowne world beſides, inſomuch that the worthy Society hath rather reap'd envy thereby than otherwiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſed as Monopolizing ſo rich and large a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, it many not be amiſſe to rectifie many mens underſtandings, how they for the moſt part have ſhowne themſelves truer Common-wealths-men than Brethren of their owne Society, or reſpectors of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate profit.</p>
            <p>Concerning Companies, and Corporations of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Trading for one place or Country, and the neceſſity thereof in generall, I have already beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in publiſhing my opinion, which for moſt part may be applyed to this in particular; but whereas it may well be expected that a Trade would not be long continued without both gaine unto the Merchants, and honour to the Kingdome, I verily beleive, it may eaſily be made appeare, that this great Trade which ſets ſo many Manufactors aworke, maintaines ſo many Marriners and Warlike Ships, if a <hi>medium</hi> of the whole ſtocke imployed therein for theſe ten yeares paſt be calculated, it will not prove to have produced five pound <hi>per centum</hi> profit unto the Intereſſed, who yet never loſt ſhip, either going or comming, through Gods particular Patronage and Providence; But for the diſhonor our King and Country ſuffers, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe Territories of the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> where we Traffique, nay, at the Imperiall Seat it ſelfe, is both
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110954:5"/>infamous and intolerable, as the violating our Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations and Articles of Peace and Commerce with them, infinite injuſtices done us, importing ten or twenty thouſand pounds ſterling at a time, vilifying and injuring our Nation, diſ-reſpecting the Perſon of our Ambaſſador, who repreſenting Soveraignety, by Law of Nations is held as Sacred, and in fine, ſo ſcandalouſly intreating us, as more honourable it is for us to have it lye concealed than publiſhed.</p>
            <p>Thus then I hope it will be granted, our Trade with <hi>Turkie,</hi> upon theſe termes, will not countervaile the diſadvantages, and how it may be remedyed fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes now.</p>
            <p>I thinke it will be confeſſed by moſt experienced men in Martiall and Maritine affaires, who are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe well enformed of ours, and the Grand <hi>Seigniors</hi> ſtrength at Sea, that we are able to ſend a Fleet into thoſe parts, (and yet not be diſarm'd at home) which by Gods aſſiſtance all the force of <hi>Turkie</hi> neither will or can encounter and it will ſeeme ſo much more probable by relation of a fight made in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi-Pelago, anno</hi> 1633. betweene the <hi>Hector,</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> and <hi>Ralph,</hi> two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants ſhips, and at leaſt fifty <hi>Turkiſh</hi> gallies, the two ſhips it is true were ſunke at laſt, and moſt of the men ſlaine, but firſt the ſhips were becalm'd, and could not ſtirre, and yet kill'd above a thouſand men upon the gallies, and ſo ruin'd the whole Fleete, as made it altogether unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable: For the <hi>Algier</hi> Pyrates, and thoſe of <hi>Tunnis,</hi> both men of warre, ſundry Merchants ſingle ſhips have happened in midſt of Fleetes, and Squadrons, and to my knowledge, by relation of thoſe very Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners of beſt repute, about the ſame yeare 1633. the ſhippes <hi>Rainebow</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> each of them ſingle in a Merchants voyage, light unawares in midſt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteene
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110954:6"/>
               <hi>Turkiſh</hi> men of warre, which had not the reſolution to aſſault them; yet doe I know the time, when two or three, nay one <hi>Turkes</hi> ſhip, hath taken an <hi>Engliſh</hi> of better ſtrength, and ſurely may doe it oftner, if God doe but permit, and we forbeare to renue againe the credit, which a long time we enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by force, and vertue of ancient acts and enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes of puiſſance and valour: yet why they ſhould thus ſingle aſſault one of our ſhips, and at other times let a ſingle ſhip paſſe by ten or twenty of theirs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt offence, this may ſerve for another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in that they direct their fights and whole voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by a kind of ſorcery, in putting two arrowes together, whereby are meant the Chriſtians and the <hi>Turkes,</hi> at certaine times and places, which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, fight and vanquiſh one another; and ſo give <hi>omen</hi> to the <hi>Turkes,</hi> for their future government and good, or bad ſucceſſe accordingly.</p>
            <p>But for this enterprize againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive forty ſhips will doe the feate, and that perhaps within a yeare or two, and happily, not onely get reſtitution of our preſent Captives, but compell the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> himſelfe to make a Peace with us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better termes than ever: Theſe forty ſale of ſhips may Ride at the Caſtle of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> all windes and weathers, interdicting all Commerce betwixt that City, and all the <hi>Turkes</hi> dominions in the white Sea, which Coaſting is above a thouſand miles voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Eaſtward, and neere a thouſand Weſtward, and out of this Sea comes a great proportion of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties proviſion, as Corne, Rice, and all manner of Pulſe, Raiſins, Lemmons, Pepper, Cinnamon, Sugar, and all other Spices, Woollen cloath, Coffe, Flax, Turbants, Indico, with all manner of Drugges, and other India Commodities: Now although perhaps we are not ſo fully informed as we might be, how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110954:6"/>conſiderable theſe proviſions are to the reliefe of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> yet ſurely by the experience we have of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts in <hi>Europe,</hi> better knowen unto us, it will ſound conſonant unto reaſon, that a City, ſo ſeated, and ſo populous as that, cannot ſubſiſt, if the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the white Sea, from whence it may with moſt convenience be furniſhed, ſhould be ſuſpended: yet I will ſeeke to prove it by another, or rather the ſame argument, though differently fram'd, which will come as home, and perhaps be ſooner granted, and that is this: All people, eſpecially multitudes, provide themſelves of neceſſaries from ſuch parts as are neereſt, and can furniſh them with the beſt, beſt cheape; now that the white Sea is able to miniſter to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> a large quantity upon theſe termes, by reaſon of its owne fruitfulneſſe, and that Cities ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, will not be much controverted, or eaſily be made appeare to reaſon, ſo that ſince the Inhabitants of the white Sea coaſt, both have and doe ſtill plow and plant for maintenance of that City, although it were poſſible, and that there were ground enough upon the blacke Sea Coaſt, to yeeld ſufficient proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and people enough to manure that ground, both which are moſt improbable, (for in ſuch caſe that ground muſt have before laine waſte, and thoſe people had no employment) yet this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be brought to paſſe, nor ſetled in a yeare or two: ſo that though the cutting off the white Sea, doe not quite ſtarve <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> yet doubtleſſe, it will bring them to a great ſtraite, and in a ſhort time raiſe the price of all proviſions and Merchandize, which us'd to come from thence, ſo much as will eaſily cauſe a tumultuous and rude multitude to rebell, and render themſelves lyable to become a booty, or elſe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> to a Peace with us, eſpecially when they underſtand, and ſee we deſire nothing but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110954:7"/>juſtice for the injuries we received, and will then be as willing to entertaine any honorable compoſition, and termes of friendſhip as they themſelves can wiſh.</p>
            <p>Now though this ſhould not fully take effect, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it will quickly be acknowledged by men of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that to hinder the intercourſe and commerce of ſo many Kingdomes by Sea, for ſome thouſand miles circuit, cannot be ſo inconſiderable a thing as not to make them weary of it in a ſhort time, and that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Caſtles of <hi>Coſtantinople,</hi> there is ſcarce any Towne or Fort upon the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Coaſt, which this Fleet, with Gods aſſiſtance, were not able to batter downe to ground, and ſacke at pleaſure; where, if they found no other riches, may lade themſelves with ſlaves, and ſell for ready money in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> The Towne of <hi>Algier</hi> it ſelfe is very ſtrong, yet with aſſiſtance of thoſe Moores, which are alwaies at grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enmity with them, is not thought able long to withſtand a parcell of this force, eſpecially when they ſhall conſider the hazzard in contracting with us, when making and keeping Peace, they may prey upon all the world beſides: And even at ſelfe-ſame time, when once it ſhall appeare, as in likeli-hood it will, that fewer ſhips can doe the ſervice at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the reſt may for <hi>Algier,</hi> and rove amongſt the Iſlands, and Turkiſh ſhore, where they cannot want bread and meate to furniſh the whole Fleet, and ſlaves to make money of, defraying their other charges.</p>
            <p>And whereas it will be objected, how both the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Venetians</hi> will be glad to ſee, and continue us in this variance with the Grand <hi>Seigniour,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to keepe us from ever being reconciled againe for advantagement of their owne Trade, although I conceive as afore, that we had better never have Peace with him upon ſuch diſadvantage and diſhonour, yet I hope it may appeare by other arguments, how
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110954:7"/>it is very probable the Turkie Trade will not be loſt for ever by theſe proceedings. For firſt, <hi>Marſeils</hi> is worne out of ſhipping, and almoſt all that little trade they drave of late, hath beene in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſels. The uſe of the <hi>Venetian</hi> cloath is likewiſe much decreaſed, but we muſt prevaile with them to forbeare the Trade ſo long as this enterprize is a foote, which they may well condeſcend unto, in recompence of the benefit they receive by our alliance, ſince of themſelves they cannot put ten ſhips to Sea, and moſt of the Woolls wherewith they make their Cloath is brought to them from <hi>Spaine</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bottomes: Beſides the trade and friendſhip of <hi>Venice,</hi> unleſſe they be alſo as deſirous to continue it, doth leſſe import us, than that of any other Chriſtian ſtate of note; for moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident it is, we are not onely not beholding to them for any trade, but that little we have by importati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Currants, may chance be found dammage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Kingdome, in that the quantity we bring from thence, coſts yearely ſeventy thouſand pounds ſterling, paid all in ready money, which for this cauſe we ſend from <hi>Legorne</hi> thither, and otherwiſe perhaps might bring in <hi>ſpecie</hi> into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in caſe the <hi>Turke</hi> ſhould never be reconciled to us againe, which his owne intereſt in commerce, need of our cloath, and dammages we can doe him, will likely urge to, the State of <hi>Venice</hi> will queſtionleſſe be willing to grant us a Staple in their Gulph, from whence our cloath might be tranſported, as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times it was, to greater profit, by <hi>Turkes, Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> to all parts of Turkie: The like may moſt commodiouſly be done from <hi>Legorne,</hi> which out of ſome experience had in thoſe parts, I know is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed at preſent, and make no ſcruple, but may be perfected hereafter in ſuch ample manner, as we ſhall ſtand in need of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110954:8"/>
But ſince this enterprize will not onely be a matter of great expence, but that by the Law of Nations, a Warre ſhould not be made without preceding inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, it may be requiſite that the Captives be firſt demanded by an extraordinary Ambaſſador, or ſome Gentleman, ſent expreſſe to the Grand <hi>Seignior;</hi> which one way or other will be a notable advantage to us, for if it take effect, it will prevent the charge and trouble of ſo great an expedition; if not, the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in the meane time, may in a faire way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their eſtates, which at preſent are above 300. thouſand pounds, and the Ambaſſador with the whole Nation retire themſelves for <hi>England:</hi> in both which perhaps we may come ſhort, not only if we go on over-haſtily, but alſo if we ſhould omit requiring reſtitution firſt in a faire way, for they queſtionleſſe will have notice, and even upon ſuſpicion ſeek to keepe beforehand by intercepting our Ambaſſador, Nation, and whole Eſtates; Which conſiderations how ever weake, I am bold humbly to preſent to their deepe wiſdomes that can beſt refine them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110954:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
